<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI version="5.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Visualizations</title>
                <editor>
                    <persName xml:id="medavis">
                        <surname>Davis</surname>
                        <forename sort="1">Matthew</forename>
                        <forename sort="2">Evan</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <pubPlace/>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>No part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system,
                        or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic, mechanical, or
                        otherwise, without the written permission of the publisher.</p>
                </availability>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc xml:id="visualization.html">
                <bibl>Information about the archive</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>One of the things I use to help me think through various issues in my teaching and
                scholarship are visualizations. Generally, these take the form of charts and graphs
                that illustrate aspects of the work, such as my <ref
                    target="http://www.sandbox.matthewedavis.net/comparison_chart.html">layout of
                    the speakers</ref> in late medieval place-and-scaffold drama alongside the
                various stages they're performing on, or my <ref
                    target="http://www.sandbox.matthewedavis.net/network_simulator.html">attempt to
                    illustrate</ref> the corrosive influence of ideologically-motivated scholarship
                on the transmittal of ideas via networks. In both these cases, the visualization is
                intended to help you see the topic in a way that text may not provide. A mostly
                complete list of the visualizations I've put together and where they can be found is
                available on my professional site, as most of them are not Lydgate related and thus
                aren't germane to what this site is intended for.</p>
            <p>The primary visualization that is attached to this project, however, is not a chart
                or graph. Rather, it is my <ref
                    target="/Model/three/examples/chantry_chapel.html"
                    >model</ref> of the Clopton chantry chapel at Holy Trinity, Long Melford. Since
                the verses by Lydgate in that chapel exist on the walls rather than in a codex it
                becomes necessary to move around the space to see them all, as I've written about
                    <ref target="http://www.matthewedavis.net/node/14">elsewhere</ref>. In thinking
                about transcribing and displaying the verses online, then, I wanted to be able to
                replicate some of the experience of being inside the chapel space and simultaneously
                viewing and not viewing everything at the same time. The model is my attempt to do
                so, and more about the peculiarities of this particular model and how it was
                constructed can be found <ref
                    target="/archive.html#construction"
                >here</ref>.</p>
            <p>It should be noted that you can access the model in two ways through the site. The
                first is via the link in the paragraph above, which will take you to a view of the
                chapel as you just walk in, looking towards the carved hand (I hesitate to say
                manicule, as it's not pointing, but it serves the same function) at the beginning of
                the <emph>Testament</emph> verses. The second is by clicking on the "view model"
                link in the upper left corner of verses from the chapel (where the icon for the
                gathering, leaf, and page are in those codices I have a collation for). Clicking on
                that link will take you to the model, but looking at the particular verse you
                navigated to the site from. In both cases, however, you can center your view on
                other items in the space (indicated by a note in the upper right of the model) and
                click to go to the transcription and facing image of that item.</p>
            <p>One final note: while I don't think they're particularly useful in terms of
                navigating the items on this site (the "Works" and "Manuscripts" tabs above are more
                useful in that regard) or speaking to specific aspects of the Lydgate corpus I also
                have two visualizations built in part on the work I did theorizing the prototype of
                the Advanced Research Consortium's <ref target="https://bigdiva.org/">BigDIVA</ref>
                project. The intent for these was to provide a quick visual reference regarding how
                Lydgate's works connect with their material witnesses, the other works they are
                currently found alongside, and the other authors that are found alongside Lydgate in
                his material corpus. This was done in the service of a larger intellectual interest
                I have in the imperfect encoding and transmission of information in material
                objects. As such, they exist primarily as an aid for talks given at the
                International Congress on Medieval Studies at Western Michigan University and the
                International Medieval Congress at the University of Leeds, but may be useful for
                someone thinking about how particular poems relate to each other across multiple
                witnesses. A two-dimensional network visualization tool can be found <ref
                    target="/forcedirect.php">here</ref>, while a
                three-dimensional visualization of the same data can be found <ref
                    target="/3d_graph/3d_graph.php">here</ref>.
                Both of these items should be considered prototypes—really one-offs for illustrative
                purposes—but they are included in case others find them useful.</p>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
