<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="tei_ms.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI version="5.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Contact the Editor</title>
                <editor>
                    <persName xml:id="medavis">
                        <surname>Davis</surname>
                        <forename sort="1">Matthew</forename>
                        <forename sort="2">Evan</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <pubPlace/>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>No part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system,
                        or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic, mechanical, or
                        otherwise, without the written permission of the publisher.</p>
                </availability>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc xml:id="contact.html">
                <bibl>About the editor and contact information.</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Dr. Matthew Evan Davis currently serves as a ZKS-Lendrum Postdoctoral Fellow, with a
                title of Assitant Professor (Research), at the <ref
                    target="https://www.durham.ac.uk/research/institutes-and-centres/medieval-early-modern-studies/"
                    >Institute for Medieval and Early Modern Studies</ref> at <ref
                    target="https://www.durham.ac.uk/homepage/">Durham University</ref> for the year
                2022. Prior to that served as a Postdoctoral Fellow with the <ref
                    target="http://scds.ca/about-the-centre/">Lewis and Ruth Sherman Centre for
                    Digital Scholarship</ref> at <ref target="http://www.mcmaster.ca">McMaster
                    University</ref>, held a Lindsey Young Visiting Faculty Fellowship
                at the <ref target="http://www.utk.edu">University of Tennessee's</ref>
                <ref target="http://marco.utk.edu">Marco Institute</ref> and served as the <ref
                    target="http://www.clir.org">Council for Library and Information
                Resources</ref>/Mellon Postdoctoral Fellow in Data Curation for Medieval Studies at
                    <ref target="http://www.ncsu.edu">North Carolina State University</ref>. While
                at North Carolina State he worked as part of the team on two similar projects — the
                    <ref target="http://piers.iath.virginia.edu">Piers Plowman Electronic
                    Archive</ref> and the <ref target="http://www.siegeofjerusalem.org">Siege of
                    Jerusalem Electronic Archive</ref>, as well the Manuscript DNA project and the
                    <ref target="http://www.mesa-medieval.org">Medieval Electronic Scholarly
                    Alliance</ref>, an aggregator and discussion space for digital scholarly and
                cultural heritage work regarding the Middle Ages.</p>
            <p>His interest in Lydgate began with a visit to the Clopton chantry chapel for his
                dissertation work on the varying significations of Mary Magdalene during the
                fifteenth century in East Anglia. Once there, he found the connections between the
                art, architecture, and verses on the chapel walls fascinating and reminscent of the
                ways in which text and decoration work together in illuminated manuscripts. The
                added performative dimension of the chapel as a religious space and the display of
                the decoration in three dimensions sparked an in interest in the poems depicted
                there, which eventually grew into the goal of the present archive: to document all
                of Lydgate's minor works.</p>
            <p>Besides his work on Lydgate, Dr. Davis also works on the staging practices of
                medieval drama, cultural transmission through translation and reception, the history
                of the book, and material and digital curation as a means of preserving both the
                material object and the connections between the object, the content contained by
                that object, and its cultural milieu.</p>
            <p>His CV may be seen <ref target="CV.html">here</ref>, and he may be contacted via
                email at <ref target="mailto:editor@minorworksoflydgate.net"
                    >editor@minorworksoflydgate.net</ref>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
