<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="tei_ms.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI version="5.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Minor Works of John Lydgate</title>
                <title type="sub">a Virtual Archive</title>
                <editor>
                    <persName xml:id="medavis">
                        <surname>Davis</surname>
                        <forename sort="1">Matthew</forename>
                        <forename sort="2">Evan</forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <pubPlace/>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>No part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system,
                        or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic, mechanical, or
                        otherwise, without the written permission of the publisher.</p>
                </availability>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc xml:id="index.html">
                <bibl>Index page text for the Minor Works of John Lydgate.</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Welcome to a virtual archive of the "minor" works of the fifteenth-century poet, John
                Lydgate.</p>
            <p>The goals of this project are twofold: first, it is an attempt to make some version
                of the manuscripts and other media containing the works of Lydgate that exist in
                less than twenty witnesses more accessible to scholars of the poet, students who may
                have only read them in print editions, and individuals interested in manuscripts as
                artifacts in their own right. To this end, it is intended to provide not a critical
                edition of these poems, but to accurately transcribe and record the variations in
                the witnesses – changes in the language, omissions, and insertions – that are
                obscured sometimes by the traditional editorial process, without privileging one
                witness over another. In this way the project might be considered an archive as
                Trevor Owens <ref
                    target="https://blogs.loc.gov/thesignal/2014/02/what-do-you-mean-by-archive-genres-of-usage-for-digital-preservers/"
                    >describes</ref> it, as "effectively ... a kind of collection of materials that
                hang together for a very particular reason."</p>
            <p>Second, this project is meant to bridge a gap between the digital world, where
                anything that cannot be concretely categorized is often left by the wayside, and the
                physical object with its rich set of significations. This goal is less about the
                archive as understood by the methodologies of archival theory or concentration on and
                analysis of textual content. Instead, it is an attempt at praxis regarding some
                theories about how to best preserve the messy, analogue, digitally liminal aspects
                of the physical object that also encode meaning. To this end, rather than the
                standard TEI document schema, which privleges the content of the text on the page
                and renders secondary presentation, paratext, and physical structure of the material
                object an <ref
                    target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/fr/html/PH.html#PH-bov"
                    >alternative TEI schema</ref> privileging the manuscript page as an object
                alongside its textual content has been used throughout. Additionally, <ref
                    target="/Model/three/examples/chantry_chapel.html">visualizations</ref>, icons,
                and other tools have been or are planned to be used to continually remind the viewer
                of the materiality of these items. In this way, the hope is that the physical object
                is described and displayed virtually in a way that preserves the social,
                interdisciplinary, and historical connections made by the physical object itself
                while also holding to common and accepted metadata standards.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
