<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="tei_ms.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI version="5.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="Testament">
                <title>Editorial Apparatus</title>
                <author>
                    <persName xml:id="medavis">
                        <surname>Davis</surname>
                        <forename sort="1">Matthew</forename>
                        <forename sort="2">Evan</forename>
                    </persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <pubPlace/>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>No part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system,
                        or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic, mechanical, or
                        otherwise, without the written permission of the publisher.</p>
                </availability>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc xml:id="apparatus.html">
                <bibl>Editorial apparatus describing the transcription methodology for the Clopton
                    Chantry Chapel.</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="draft">
            <listChange>
                <change when="2014-06-28" who="#medavis" status="draft">Added xml:id block to
                    sourceDesc.</change>
                <change when="2014-06-27" who="#medavis" status="draft">Modified editorial to remove
                    references to supplied text.</change>
                <change when="2014-09-22" who="#medavis" status="draft">Modified xml:id block to
                    sourceDesc in order to connect apparati to specific texts</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="GeneralEditorial">
        <body>
            <p>I utilize the system described by Michelle P. Brown in her <emph rend="italic">Guide
                    to Western Historical Scripts from Antiquity to 1600</emph> (Toronto, 1993), but
                modified for the purposes of presentation on the web. This is especially evident in
                the case of painted items like the Clopton Chapel. Generally speaking, though:</p>
            <list type="bulleted">
                <item>Capitals, whether rubricated or illuminated, are given the most prominent
                        color of the glyph proper. They are also set to the line height they appear to have in the text.
                        So, for example, a two-line capital W that is predominantly red will appear
                        thusly:
                    <p><hi rend="capital_2_red">W</hi>han that Aprille with his shoures soote.</p>
                    <p>The droghte of Marche hath perced to the roote</p>
                </item>
                <item>Missing capitals will have a blank space provided, mimicking their appearance
                        in the text. The letter will be included in the XML, though, with a <code>@rend</code> attribute of "hidden." Any guide letters will be indicated via note.
                </item>
                <item>Underlined text will be rendered thusly: <hi rend="underline">text</hi>. It will be modfied still further should the underlining be in a different color than the main body of the text.  For example, a red underline will appear as follows: <hi rend="underline_red">text</hi>.
                </item>
                <item>Paraph marks will mimic their color and line height in the text. So, for
                        example, a single-line blue paraph mark will appear thusly: 
                    <p><hi rend="blue_pilcrow">¶</hi>Heere bigineeth the miller his tale</p>
                </item>
                <item>Letters touched by rubrication will be rendered thusly: <hi rend="touched"
                            >T</hi>.
                </item>
                <item>Expanded abbreviations in the text are indicated thusly: ex<emph
                            rend="italic">am</emph>ple.
                </item>
                <item>Damaged but legible material is indicated thusly:
                        <damage>example</damage>.
                </item>
                <item>A gap in the text through damage is indicated thusly:<gap quantity="7"
                            unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>, where the number of dots indicate the
                        likely number of missing letters based on the other witnesses.
                </item>
                <item>Insertions will be rendered inline with the text as though they were on the
                        same line, and will appear thusly: <add>insertion</add>. Any unusual
                        characteristics regarding the insertion will be mentioned via note.
                </item>
                <item>Deletions will be rendered thusly: <del>deletion</del>
                </item>
                <item>Substitutions will be rendered inline with the text, and will appear thusly: <subst>
                            <del>inertion</del>
                            <add>insertion</add>
                        </subst>. Any unusual characteristics regarding the substitution will be
                        mentioned via note.
                </item>
                <item>Specific issues regarding the text will be indicated via a footnote either
                        immediately after the item referenced or at the end of the line. They have
                        been color-coded to indicate the type of note they are: <list
                            type="bulleted">
                            <item>Explanatory notes provide the reasoning for the editorial choices
                                made, with reference to the image provided. They are indicated
                                    thusly:<note n="explanatory">The text for the explanatory note will appear like this</note>.</item>
                            <item>Informational notes provide non-editorial contextual information
                                such as particular scribal renderings or relationships between the
                                witnesses. They are indicated thusly:<note
                                    n="informational">The text for the informational note will appear like this</note>.</item>
                            <item>Notes unrelated either to the specifics of the text or containing
                                both explanatory and informational elements are indicated
                                    thusly:<note n="other">The text for all other notes will appear like this</note>.</item>
                        </list>
                    
                </item>
            </list>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
